You found a job as a waitress and a place to live.
Kau diterima jadi pramusaji, juga punya apartemen.
But this bed is awful.
Tapi ranjangnya jelek.
It almost falls over just when I sit on it.
Diduduki saja langsung menceng.
It will collapse if you lie on it, Nina.
Kalau Nina pakai tidur, pasti roboh.
I'll sleep on this bed. You're better off sleeping on that sofa.
Aku tidur di kasur ini. Nina tidur di sofa saja.
There's no bed here for you.
Kau tak tidur di sini.
You go back to Dr. Reichwein in Munich.
Kau ke tempat Dr. Reichwein di München.
How come?
Kenapa?
Isn't it obvious? You need to go to school.
"Kenapa"? Kau harus sekolah.
I don't need to go to school.
Aku tak perlu sekolah.
Then how will you learn?
Terus, belajarmu bagaimana?
You'll teach me, Nina.
Diajari Nina.
School is not the only thing. You'll never make friends like this.
Bukan masalah belajar saja. Nanti kau tak dapat teman.
I've got friends. You and Tenma.
Aku punya teman. Nina dan Tenma.
Besides, you know you'll be lonely without me around, Nina.
Lagi pula, Nina pasti kesepian tanpaku.
Nice try, but you're going back to Munich.
Pokoknya, kau kembali ke München.
No way! I'm not going to Munich!
Tidak mau! Aku tak mau ke München!
Wait, Nina. Are you going there again today?
Tunggu, Nina. Kau mau ke sana lagi?
Come on! Give it up, would you?
Hei, tunggu! Kau tak kapok juga?
Every day, you go to the same place.
Tiap hari kau ke sana terus.
No matter how many times you go, you'll never remember anything!
Sesering apa pun ke sana, kau takkan ingat apa-apa!
Nina!
Nina!
This is where we lived.
Dulu kami tinggal di sini.
Mother and I… and Johan.
Ibu, aku,
That day, Johan was dragged down these stairs and taken away.
Hari itu, Johan diseret di tangga ini dan dibawa pergi.
No! Don't! Let go!
Tidak! Jangan! Lepaskan!
Mother! Nina!
Ibu! Nina!
No…
Bukan…
Nina is the name I use now.
Nina adalah namaku yang sekarang.
But what name did I have then?
Tapi saat itu siapa namaku?
Nina? Anna?
Nina? Anna?
What is…
Siapa
my name?
namaku?
The car Johan was taken in went down this road.
Mobil yang membawa Johan lewat jalan ini.
Keeping secrets from him is a no-no.
Tak boleh merahasiakan sesuatu darinya.
Children gathered for what were called book readings…
Anak-anak berkumpul di sini untuk membaca buku…
here at the Red Rose Mansion.
di Rumah Mawar Merah.
The lock's been broken.
Kuncinya sudah dirusak.
Here, they tried to create superior students.
Di sini tempat eksperimen menciptakan murid unggulan.
What is a superior student?
Apa itu murid unggulan?
Johan…
Johan.
And…
Lalu…
Who did such a thing?
Siapa yang melakukan itu?
He ran.
Dia kabur.
Johan ran away…
Johan kabur
through the rose bushes.
melalui hamparan bunga mawar.
Ouch!
Aduh!
Are you okay?
Kau tak apa?
This pain…
Rasa sakit ini…
Could it be…
Mungkinkah…
THREE FROGS.
THREE FROGS (TIGA KATAK)
I waited in this room…
Aku menunggu di kamar ini.
for Mother to return…
Menunggu Ibu
and for Johan to return.
dan Johan pulang.
I read this picture book as I waited.
Aku menunggu sambil membaca buku cerita ini.
THE NAMELESS MONSTER
MONSTER TANPA NAMA
People can become…
Orang bisa menjadi
whatever they want to be.
apa pun yang dia inginkan.
Franz Bonaparta…
Franz Bonaparta,
Bonaparta, the man who held the book readings at the Red Rose Mansion…
orang yang mengadakan pembacaan buku di Rumah Mawar Merah.
I read his book here in this room.
Buku ini kubaca di sini.
I was waiting for Johan to return.
Sambil menunggu Johan pulang.
I smiled and faced the door…
Sambil tersenyum dan menghadap pintu,
and said…
aku bilang…
Welcome back.
Selamat datang.
"Welcome back."
"Selamat datang."
Welcome back!
Selamat datang!
Now, come with me.
Nah, mari ikut.
The door never opened!
Pintunya tak terbuka!
Even when I said "Welcome back," the door didn't open!
Meski kubilang, "Selamat datang," pintunya tak terbuka.
It won't open! It won't!
Tak terbuka!
You see, I…
Karena aku…
I remember now! I…
Aku ingat!
Stop it, Nina!
Sudahlah, Nina!
You don't have to remember! You don't have to remember anything!
Tak perlu ingat! Kau tak perlu mengingatnya!
It's the same with me! I've got tons of awful memories!
Aku juga sama! Punya banyak kenangan buruk!
But you don't have to remember them anymore!
Tapi kau tak perlu mengingatnya lagi!
Fine! I'll go to Dr. Reichwein!
Baiklah. Aku mau ke tempat Dr. Reichwein!
But you'll come with me! We'll go back together!
Tapi, Nina harus ikut! Kita ke sana bersama.
Let's do what Tenma said.
Ayo ikuti pesan Tenma.
From now on, let's make…
Mulai sekarang, mari kita kumpulkan
happy memories.
kenangan indah.
PRAGUE POLICE STATION (CZECH REPUBLIC)
KEPOLISIAN PRAHA (REPUBLIK CEKO)
Hold on a minute, Chief Detective!
Tunggu, Pak Kepala Detektif!
How come I can only sit next to the detective and listen?
Kenapa aku cuma duduk dan mendengarkan di samping detektif?
We're doing our very best to accommodate your request.
Kami berusaha sebaik mungkin memenuhi permintaanmu.
Your very best?
Berusaha sebaik mungkin?
You're only giving me 30 minutes with each person!
Aku cuma diberi 30 menit mewawancarai setiap saksi.
You can listen in. Isn't that enough?
Mendengarkan saja cukup, 'kan?
You have to realize that even allowing this is an extreme exception.
Kau harus sadar izin ini juga pengecualian.
It took a lot for us to even be able to question five witnesses.
Kami susah payah agar bisa memeriksa lima saksi ini.
But we should take this chance to get as much info as possible!
Tapi kita harus manfaatkan kesempatan ini untuk menggali!
-You just don't get it. -Huh?
- Kau naif. - Apa?
These people were kids in that book reading club.
Mungkin mereka takkan mau menceritakan masa lalunya.
They won't want to talk about their pasts.
Mereka dulunya mengikuti pembacaan buku di sana.
Well, I doubt there's any question that all the bones that were found
Bisa dipastikan tulang-tulang yang kita temukan
are somehow connected with the former Czechoslovakia secret police.
terkait dengan para mantan polisi rahasia Cekoslowakia.
But you know,
Tapi tahu sendiri,
the truth around these kinds of things usually remains a mystery.
fakta di balik kasus macam ini biasanya selamanya jadi misteri.
This is the detective in charge of this case.
Dia detektif penanggung jawab kasus ini.
This is the attorney, Mr. Verdemann, from Germany.
Ini pengacara, Pak Verdemann, dari Jerman.
I'll leave the rest to you.
Tolong urus, ya.
I'm Detective Suk.
Aku Detektif Suk.
Nice to meet you.
Salam kenal.
I've already made a list of questions.
Aku sudah buat daftar pertanyaannya.
Please only do as I say.
Tolong ikuti arahanku.
You're only here as an observer.
Kau di sini hanya sebagai pengamat.
3 Cerveny Street, otherwise known as the Red Rose Mansion.
Jalan Cerveny 3, atau Rumah Mawar Merah.
This is how it looks now that it's burned down.
Beginilah kondisinya setelah kebakaran.
Is it true that you participated
Apa benar Anda berpartisipasi
in the book readings that took place here in 1968, Mr. Erno?
dengan pembacaan buku di sana pada tahun 1968, Pak Erno?
Well, sir?
Pak?
Do you know a man by the name of Franz Bonaparta?
Apa Anda kenal pria bernama Franz Bonaparta?
Will you please keep quiet?
Bisakah kau diam?
There's no time.
Waktu kita sempit, 'kan?
I want to do this carefully.
Kita harus berhati-hati.
You'll get nothing out of them by being careful. Do you want that?
Kalau berhati-hati, takkan ada hasilnya. Itu maumu?
You have no idea how much trouble we went through to get this far.
Kau tak paham betapa susahnya mendapatkan saksi-saksi ini.
I'm not sad.
Aku tak sedih.
I always thought this mansion was my emotional foundation.
Kukira Rumah Mawar Merah itu adalah dukungan emosiku.
But seeing the mansion burn down, I thought… How do I put it?
Tapi saat melihatnya terbakar, bagaimana, ya, bilangnya?
I thought I'd feel sad.
Kukira aku akan sedih.
Did you feel nostalgic for it?
Apa Anda merasakan nostalgia?
Nostalgia?
Nostalgia?
That's right. This place was like a school to you, wasn't it?
Ya. Rumah itu bagi Anda seperti sekolah, 'kan?
Mr. Verdemann! Please keep quiet! Only the questions I prepared--
Pak Verdemann! Tolong diam! Cuma pertanyaanku saja…
I don't know if I do…
Entahlah.
Sadness… Nostalgia…
Kesedihan, nostalgia…
Emotional scars? What do you mean?
Luka hati? Maksudmu?
I mean, did your participation in the book readings
Apakah partisipasi Anda pada pembacaan buku di sana
have any effect on your life now?
berdampak pada hidup Anda sekarang?
No, not really.
Tidak, tidak juga.
How about on your family?
Kalau keluarga Anda?
You don't have to answer that. That's your right.
Anda tak perlu jawab. Anda punya hak.
I'm divorced.
Aku sudah bercerai.
It wasn't like my wife and I were on bad terms or anything.
Bukannya hubunganku dan istriku buruk.
Our children…
Anak-anak kami…
Both of our sons killed themselves.
Kedua putra kami bunuh diri.
They didn't have any problems in particular,
Mereka juga tak punya masalah pribadi,
but for some reason, they both…
tapi entah kenapa mereka…
I wonder why they killed themselves.
Kenapa mereka bunuh diri, ya?
What are you implying?
Apa maksudmu?
I'm saying that your questions are too much by the book.
Daftar pertanyaanmu terlalu prosedural.
How much information have you gotten using them anyway?
Dengan metode ini, apa saja yang sudah kau gali?
You're typical of youngsters nowadays.
Dasar anak muda zaman sekarang.
I bet you go by the book when you pick up women too.
Saat mendekati perempuan, pasti kau juga ikuti prosedur, ya?
What are you, my father?
Kau seperti ayahku saja.
I don't have a father, but I sure wouldn't want one like you.
Aku tak punya ayah, tapi aku tak mau ayah sepertimu.
Next, please.
Selanjutnya, silakan.
Memories of the book readings, huh?
Kenangan dari pembacaan buku, ya?
Tell us anything you remember, no matter how trivial.
Mohon ceritakan apa saja yang Anda ingat.
"The God of Peace is always very busy."
"Dewa Kedamaian selalu sibuk."
What's that all about?
Kenapa tiba-tiba menyela?
"He was so busy playing the horn, he had no time to look in the mirror."
"Dia sibuk bermain trompet sampai tak sempat berkaca."
That's from The God of Peace by Klaus Poppe.
Itu kutipan Dewa Kedamaian oleh Klaus Poppe.
You know this, don't you?
Anda tahu, 'kan?
Yes, I kind of remember that.
Ya, aku sepertinya ingat.
I also liked the one
Aku juga suka buku cerita
that was about a monster who went west and a monster who went east.
tentang monster yang ke barat dan monster yang ke timur.
What did you like about these books?
Apa yang Anda sukai dari buku itu?
Well… How can I put it?
Bagaimana menjelaskannya, ya?
It felt like they took me away to a different world.
Aku seperti terbuai ke dunia lain.
A different world?
Dunia lain?
Yes, and let's see…
Ya, seperti ini…
It felt like things like sadness, joy and fear didn't exist there.
Emosi seperti kesedihan, kebahagiaan, dan ketakutan, tak ada di sana.
Why did those books make you feel that way?
Kenapa buku itu memicu Anda merasakan itu?
I don't know.
Entah.
I basically wouldn't feel anything.
Aku jadi tak merasakan apa pun.
I wouldn't even need my name anymore.
Aku pun merasa tak butuh nama lagi.
It was real freedom.
Itulah kebebasan sejati.
That's how it felt.
Itu yang kurasakan.
Why did it feel that way?
Kenapa seperti itu rasanya?
Franz Bonaparta taught you there, right?
Anda diajari Franz Bonaparta, 'kan?
I guess that was the name of the guy who read to us.
Sepertinya itu salah satu nama pencerita.
These are your clearest memories of what happened at the book readings?
Jadi, itu yang paling Anda ingat dari klub baca buku ini?
My clearest memories?
Yang paling kuingat?
No.
Bukan itu.
One day, a man came to that mansion.
Suatu hari, ada pria datang ke rumah itu.
He said he was from a radio station.
Katanya dia dari stasiun radio.
He said he liked the song "Over the Rainbow."
Dia suka lagu "Over the Rainbow"
and told us the story of The Wizard of Oz.
dan dia menceritakan kisah The Wizard of Oz.
What was that man like?
Seperti apa orang itu?
Tell me about that man!
Ceritakan soal dia!
What's gotten into you?
Kau ini kenapa?
-Pull yourself together! -Tell me!
- Tenanglah! - Kumohon!
Please! Tell me anything you know!
Tolong ceritakan yang Anda tahu!
What are you trying to do?
Apa tujuanmu?
It seems like this questioning is personal to you!
Kau seperti anggap ini wawancara pribadi!
It's personal for you too, isn't it?
Bagimu juga pribadi, 'kan?
The young detective who had those murders
Detektif muda yang dikambinghitamkan
connected to the secret police pinned on him…
atas pembunuhan terkait polisi rahasia Ceko…
was you, right, Detective Suk?
Itu kau, 'kan, Detektif Suk?
You're desperate to clear yourself of suspicion.
Kau berusaha keras membersihkan namamu.
Isn't that right?
Benar, 'kan?
It's the same with me.
Aku juga sama.
My father was imprisoned as a spy for former East Germany.
Ayahku dipenjara karena dituduh mata-mata Jerman Timur.
I always believed he was falsely accused.
Aku yakin dia difitnah.
But my father really was a spy.
Tapi ternyata ayahku memang mata-mata.
I couldn't believe anything anymore.
Aku jadi sulit percaya kepada siapa pun.
I couldn't believe anything in this world anymore.
Aku tak lagi percaya dunia ini.
But now, by pursuing the case of another falsely accused man,
Tapi, dengan menyelidiki kasus korban salah tuduh lain,
I am trying to find something to believe in again.
aku ingin bisa memercayai sesuatu lagi.
The man from a radio station this man talked about…
Pria dari stasiun radio yang disinggung olehnya
He's my father.
adalah ayahku.
My father might have been involved in the brainwashing experiments
Ayahku mungkin terlibat eksperimen cuci otak
that occurred at the Red Rose Mansion.
di Rumah Mawar Merah.
We must not look away if we want to learn the real truth.
Kita tak boleh berpaling jika ingin tahu faktanya.
Say, can I leave now?
Aku sudah boleh pergi?
Just a few more minutes.
Mohon tunggu sebentar.
That guy I told you about earlier, he told me this.
Pria yang tadi kusebut pernah bilang begini.
"Get out of here fast."
"Segeralah lari dari sini.
"You'll find a beautiful place over the rainbow."
Kau akan temukan tempat indah di ujung pelangi.
"That's where your family is."
Di sanalah keluargamu berada.
"At the end of The Wizard of Oz, Dorothy makes it back home."
Di akhir cerita Penyihir Oz, Dorothy berhasil pulang.
"So you get out of here fast too."
Jadi, kau juga harus segera lari."
After that, I left that mansion forever.
Aku tak pernah kembali lagi ke rumah itu.
Can I go now?
Boleh aku pergi?
My wife and kids are waiting.
Ditunggu istri dan anakku.
Sure.
Silakan.
We must not look away.
Kita tak boleh berpaling.
That's right.
Benar.
There are two people left to question.
Tinggal dua orang lagi.
Right. Let's continue.
Baik. Mari lanjutkan.
Dieter, don't stare off into space! Hold onto this properly.
Dieter, jangan melamun! Pegang ini baik-baik.
This is your desk, after all.
Ini meja belajarmu, 'kan?
Right.
Baik.
Nina doesn't want to talk about what happened to her in Prague.
Nina tak mau membahas kejadian di Praha.
From what you told me, it sounds like she got a lot of her memories back.
Dari ceritamu, sepertinya sebagian ingatannya pulih.
But it seems she was stopped from remembering until the very end…
Tapi sepertinya dia gagal ingat sepenuhnya
thanks to you.
berkat dirimu.
Was it wrong for me to stop her?
Apa aku salah menghentikannya?
No. You did very well, Dieter.
Tidak. Dieter, usahamu bagus.
Let's finish this up quick so I can have some weisswurst and beer!
Ayo cepat rampungkan agar bisa makan sosis putih dan bir!
We ate all the weisswurst last night.
Sosis putihnya sudah habis tadi malam.
That's right! What will I do now?
Benar juga! Bagaimana ini?
Doctor!
Dr. Reichwein!
I brought you some of your favorite, weisswurst sausages.
Kubawakan sosis putih favoritmu.
You guys sure are considerate!
Kalian pengertian sekali!
Dr. Reichwein, how have you been?
Dr. Reichwein, apa kabarmu?
I'm sorry that I haven't written in so long.
Maaf, aku sudah lama tak kirim surat.
I know I've made you worry, but I'm fine.
Kau pasti cemas, tapi aku baik saja.
Dr. Reichwein, I have a favor to ask you.
Dr. Reichwein, aku butuh bantuanmu.
You know the woman Eva Heinemann, don't you?
Kau kenal Eva Heinemann, 'kan?
A certain organization is after her.
Dia diincar suatu organisasi.
I sent her to you. Please take care of her.
Kuminta dia ke tempatmu. Tolong jaga dia.
Please take care of Nina and Dieter as well.
Tolong jaga Nina dan Dieter juga.
It won't be long now.
Tak lama lagi.
I believe this is the only way for me to end all this.
Aku yakin ini satu-satunya cara mengakhiri kasus ini.
"From Kenzo Tenma."
"Dari Kenzo Tenma."
That letter arrived three days ago.
Surat itu sampai tiga hari lalu.
But Eva hasn't reached out to me.
Tapi Eva belum menghubungiku.
Where was this letter sent from?
Suratnya dikirim dari mana?
It's hard to read the postmark.
Cap posnya sulit terbaca.
Can you figure it out, Karl?
Bisa kau cari tahu, Karl?
Yes. I think I can.
Ya, mungkin bisa.
Then we'll know where Tenma is.
Jadi, kita bisa tahu Tenma di mana, ya?
But I'm bothered by this last sentence.
Tapi aku cemas dengan kalimat terakhir.
"I believe this is the only way for me to end all this."
"Aku yakin ini satu-satunya cara mengakhiri kasus ini."
All right, then. Let's finish up this desk.
Baiklah. Ayo rampungkan meja belajar Dieter.
My hand might not be so steady after that drink though.
Tapi mungkin tanganku tak stabil setelah minum.
Dr. Reichwein.
Dr. Reichwein.
I want to remember everything.
Aku ingin ingat semuanya.
Are you prepared for what you'll find?
Kau sudah siap dengan konsekuensinya?
Yes.
Ya.
I'm ready to use whatever method it takes to remember everything.
Apa pun metodenya, aku siap mengingat semuanya.
To be honest, I'd rather not do this.
Jujur saja, itu tak kusarankan.
But if that's truly what you want, then okay.
Tapi jika ini maumu, ya sudah.
Are you sure about this, Nina?
Kau siap, Nina?
Yes, Dr. Gillen.
Ya, Dr. Gillen.
-But… -Yes?
- Tapi… - Ya?
What I'm about to reveal under hypnosis just might be terrifying.
Mungkin aku akan mengungkap hal mengerikan saat dihipnosis.
Do you think you can handle it?
Dr. Gillen siap menghadapinya?
Yes, I'll be fine. We'll face these things together.
Ya. Aku siap. Kita hadapi bersama-sama.
Okay, now. Close your eyes,
Baiklah. Tutup matamu,
take a deep breath, and relax your whole body.
tarik napas dalam-dalam, dan lemaskan badanmu.
What was your mother like?
Seperti apa ibumu?
Mother…
Ibu…
Mother… was kind…
Ibu orang baik…
She sang…
Suaranya…
She sang in… a beautiful voice.
Suaranya… suaranya merdu.
The smell of bean soup.
Bau sup kacang.
And your father?
Ayahmu?
Father…
Ayah…
Father was… a government soldier.
Ayah adalah tentara.
A government soldier?
Tentara?
Have you met him?
Kau pernah bertemu ayahmu?
I've never met him.
Belum pernah.
Mother told me…
Ibu bilang
Father was killed.
Ayah dibunuh.
Mother was a political activist.
Dulu Ibu aktivis politik.
When your father was killed,
Setelah ayahmu dibunuh,
your mother, who was a political activist, then defected.
ibumu yang seorang aktivis politik mencari suaka.
Was she running from someone?
Ibumu kabur dari siapa?
At the Three Frogs… we hid.
Kami bersembunyi di penginapan Three Frogs.
But my brother… was captured by the man with glasses!
Tapi kakakku ditangkap oleh pria berkacamata!
Your brother was captured, was he?
Kakakmu ditangkap, ya?
The Red Rose Mansion!
Rumah Mawar Merah!
So many people… dead!
Banyak sekali yang mati di sana!
Your brother saw that?
Kakakmu melihatnya?
Ow! Ow!
Sakit!
Ow! The rose thorns hurt!
Aduh! Duri mawarnya menyakitkan!
Welcome back.
Selamat datang.
Nina.
Nina.
I figured out where Tenma's letter was sent from.
Aku tahu dari mana surat Tenma dikirim.
Where?
Dari mana?
Frankfurt.
Frankfurt.
Nina, you've remembered everything, haven't you?
Nina, kau sudah ingat semuanya , 'kan?
I… am not Nina.
Aku bukan Nina.
Then who are you?
Lalu siapa?
I don't want to say.
Aku tak mau bilang.
It's all right. Don't be afraid. You can tell me.
Tak apa. Tak perlu takut, ceritakan saja.
Who are you?
Kau siapa?
I don't want to say.
Aku tak mau bilang.
It's all right. Don't be afraid.
Tak apa. Jangan takut.
I'm back!
Aku pulang!
I'll… clap my hands now. When I do,
Aku akan menepuk tangan. Setelah itu,
you'll wake up!
kau akan sadar!
Nina!
Nina!
She's all right.
Dia baik-baik saja.
Did I… just say something terrible?
Apa aku menceritakan hal buruk?
No. When you were under hypnosis, you refused to say it.
Tidak. Kau menolak bicara meski dalam pengaruh hipnosis.
So you have remembered everything now.
Tapi, kau pasti sudah ingat semuanya.
TWO DAYS LATER
DUA HARI KEMUDIAN
Dr. Reichwein and Dieter, please forgive me for leaving so suddenly.
Dr. Reichwein dan Dieter, maaf aku pergi tanpa pamit.
I'm going to Frankfurt, where Tenma is.
Aku akan menemui Tenma di Frankfurt.
I know everything now.
Aku sudah tahu semuanya.
I know who I am,
Aku tahu identitasku,
where Johan came from and where he's trying to go.
dari mana asal Johan, dan destinasi yang dia tuju.
If I go, then all this can be brought to an end.
Jika aku pergi, semua ini bisa disudahi.
If I go, then Tenma can be saved.
Jika aku pergi, Tenma bisa diselamatkan.